software engineering radio episode 34
enterprise architecture
this episode is an interview with nd
longshaw he's one of the two authors of
a book on architecting enterprise
solutions patterns for high capability
internet-based systems and so this
episode will be on this topic obviously
so welcome Andy and why don't you start
by explaining a bit of your personal
background and your yeah your background
yes I was I've been working in software
for twenty years came up through the
route of being things like system
administrator and low-level coder
through to the status of principal
technologist to curate training the
grand title and then going on to do some
more real world stuff hands-on than
design of systems and going getting to
the gradual realization that technology
wasn't the solution that the technology
was really part of the problem so then I
guess this book is not about a specific
technology but rather mass patterns are
usually about the principles and the
core building blocks of how to build
these kinds of systems yes that's
certainly one of the key things here
that no matter whether you you're using
j2ee and sun hardware or whether you're
using Microsoft hardware sorry Microsoft
software and Intel based hardware the
things that you're doing in this area
are fundamentally the same so you should
really understand your motivation for
doing what you're doing before just
picking a technology and saying oh look
look what we can do with this it's like
no why are you doing that with that is
it we don't know but it just looks good
so before we delve into the patterns can
you maybe briefly explain what the core
characteristics of this particular class
of systems is what what what what's an
internet-based high performance
enterprise I think that were the buzz
words system yes I must apologize for
the title we we struggled with asses to
what between publishers and and authors
as to what the book should be called and
I mean the key and the key angle that
the pole and I came from is about
non-functional requirements so there's a
scalability availability performance
primarily but also a variety of other
non-functional such as maintainability
and extensibility this set of patents
originated when we were doing a small
amount of work on a training course if
somebody wanted to write at Sun and the
the course led nowhere but well Paul and
I were working on it we started getting
all these sort of ideas of how to view
the world we've been working in of
putting together clusters of servers
distributing software across those
servers and having to deal with variable
load and so on and so forth
so we started to think of the ility Zoar
system qualities and the fact that it's
a greater or lesser degree your
functional requirements find you capture
your functional requirements as use
cases or user stories or however you
like to do that and essentially you
could run on your functional system on
one box it's only the non-functional
requirements that start to make it
distributed and dynamic can you get into
failover and all the rest of the stuff
there's suddenly you start to get the
whole set of tricky problems and it
changes the way you architect your your
system certainly and in many ways it
changes the way you you write your
software okay so then I guess we should
get started with the first pattern it's
as I can see I've read the book but it's
a while ago so we were taking the book
as a kind of cheat sheet for me so the
first pattern is called application
server architecture sounds rather
general but I guess that's the point
it's the starting point for the detailed
patterns yes this is we went through
several tortuous eight-hour iterations
and we did initially try to classify
that the patterns in some way because we
knew we need to need made sense to have
it manageable and split them up somehow
and we'd come fairly quickly come to the
split of performance patterns and
maintenance sort of evolution evolution
patterns and control patterns and no
doubt of those three classifications but
there was something lurking around
where where you actually come in and we
figured out that essentially this made
sense once you decided that essentially
your software was going to sit in one
pretty much in one housing so one
runtime and then you then get instances
of that runtime either multiple
instances on the same machine or
instances on different machines and you
start to load bounce across and failover
between them and so on so that's where
the application server architecture came
from this thing of saying rather than
having a dedicated say payment server
over there a dedicated shopping cart
server over here a dedicated content
management server over here that
essentially a lot of the systems were
working with all of the functionality
was put onto one one server instance and
the way you achieved
scalability availability and so on was
by repeating instances of that
combination of software so if you talk
about application server architecture
then you don't mean that you should use
a j2ee application server but rather
that you have a certain set of buffs of
components or applications running on
that machine and that thing can be
easily replicated is that what you're
saying essentially yes but what we found
find is that if you're dealing in with
these sort of Internet technology based
systems so you have it's almost like
when you come in as a starting point you
say right uh my systems are out to a
large potential variable group if it's
across the internet I'm using HTTP HTML
dot therefore I'm gonna have a SPS or
servlets if I'm working in the Java
world as my front-end and therefore I
need something to house those in and
therefore you know I've got an
application server and in the middle
Microsoft world it's pretty much the
same thing except for the fact the
application servers really hidden as
part of the operating system and then
you get the dotnet framework on top of
that and that provides you essentially
with the same sort of application server
so the core element is the application
server and then I guess I mean can you
actually really run all parts of an
enterprise application on an application
server or do you need some some special
kinds of things well this is this is
that this is that the
key issue is that not everything fits in
the application server model the
application server models very driven by
user events so a user comes in hits a
particular page or particular piece of
functionality and that triggers the the
processing there are other things that
want to happen in a system so in an
e-commerce system you may well want to
mail out to your customers so you're
dealing with the same data people who've
been to your website and registered and
you want to use the registration
information and so on but the actual
trigger for that event is completely
different it's a time thing that once a
day or once a week you want to send out
a bulk of email to those people and so
really sitting that in the application
server if you tried to put that in the
application server you started getting
too tortuous triggering mechanisms that
the application servers really weren't
designed to work with so that's where
you get onto the idea of the peripheral
specialist elements but these are things
that are designed particularly to to do
a job that doesn't fit in the same it's
if it's in the style of the application
server one thing that I find interesting
is that so you wrote a book about
patterns for enterprise applications and
they contain patterns as we will see in
a moment for all kinds of things like
performance scalability and still you
say you should run things on an
application server now if you ask the
application server vendors they'll say
how you know a separation of concerns
you just write the business logic and
then the application server takes care
of all those non-functional things and
from reading your book and from from
talking to you I get the impression that
that's not not not completely the case
well there's definitely there's there's
several angles to this one is that these
inside the box and outside the box and
so inside the box being inside the
application server so when you're inside
the application server the separation of
concerns is a good idea because you
don't want just a bunch of spaghetti
code inside your application server
however once you once you start getting
to the to the levels of machine
management then the having having
separate machines to do different jobs
you get in you've got it you've got a
balance different forces so you've got
the question of whether you're actually
utilizing the hardware correctly and one
of the one of the
we listed out our set of non-functional
requirement those sorry non-functional
characteristics such as scalability
availability and so on and really the
the key one that it's almost like the
the requirement nobody dares speak of is
cost a non functional requirement is
probably one of the biggest sorry cost
is probably one of the biggest
non-functional requirements in any
project and so if I were to say well
grades we will separate concerns and we
will have dedicated web servers
dedicated business object servers
dedicated database servers and so on and
of course each of these has got to be
available so we need at least two
machines for each of them and so on
suddenly the cost starts to skyrocket in
terms of hardware and in terms of
ongoing support for the hardware so
that's why there's a balance to be had
between what should be specialist
peripheral and what should be in the
application server architecture because
the application server architecture then
can do a variety of jobs while still
running on say three machines you can
still get the right level of
availability from three machines and
they're all running a reasonably 60%
usage rate most of the time which
managers like they'd like to see that
the money that put into invested in
hardware is being used a lot at the time
okay so let's move on to the first
section of non umbrella patterns of real
stuff which is called system performance
patterns and I guess it deals mainly
with performance and scalability issues
I would expect so what are the main
building blocks of making systems you
know scalable and perform well the first
thing is just just to clarify we've
tended to use the term elements for
things because some of some of these
patterns apply equally to hardware and
software and if you start using terms
like components then there's a lot of
overloaded meaning in the software world
and also in the hardware world
components people tend to think maybe
down to chip level components and ICS
and so on so we did so we came up with
this this term of elements as a
compromise so we talked about things
like active redundant elements so if we
when we looked they did this they're
probably the three key illa T's
softcore sorry system causes in this
area our performance scalability and
availability so the the active redundant
elements addresses really the availab
available 'ti to say ok i have a machine
again i could start off with one single
machine great it does all the functional
things I need
but then if it falls over my users
haven't got anything to any application
to run so what can I do
ok the easiest thing I can do that to a
degree it's a bit like ok what's the
simplest thing I can possibly do I can
add another machine that if that one
falls over the other one starts up
either automatically or it's brought
online so I some manual mechanism so
that's fairly straightforward okay so we
failover from one to the other but it's
ended questions around that of it's that
second machine of the same capacity and
does it need to be the same capacity and
again we get into this this
non-functional comment of cost can we
afford to have two machines of the same
capacity one of them that's just sat
there completely idle all of the time so
that's one side of the questioning and
and the other side is how do we do this
failover so ok we have potentially a
piece of hardware up front that it's a
content management so switch that
decides where to send requests so it'll
send all the requests to one server and
then if there if that fails if it
detects the failure then it can send
them to the other server ah
but what if that content management
switch fails okay so we need active
redundant content management switches so
this is why we got into calling them
elements because then so there's this
failover potentially between hardware
devices such as that between software
servers such as the the Sun workstation
or the you know the rack the rack mount
is server that the application servers
running on and also between the software
instance of themselves so potentially
you have multiple application server
instances running on one piece of
hardware within partitioned virtual
machines and you can fail you can one of
those could crash and then the de load
for that goes on you know goes onto
another one that's sitting there waiting
not to doing anything but obviously this
is this is a slightly artificial when we
get to that stage you
really designed it like that you'd say
well okay why have I got an instance you
sat there waiting doing the thing can't
I use this usefully so then that leads
on to the thinking of load-balanced
elements where we've got the same sort
of scenario we have one or more what we
started to turn functionally identical
elements so they do the same function
but potentially they've got more or less
power so in a typical load balance
scenario you have a set of elements set
of servers say that are functionally
identical and also pretty much identical
in terms of power but there's no reason
that has to be the case you know
potentially you can start with the
smaller server and then as your load
grows you get more customers into your
e-commerce site you can afford more
Hardware you get a bigger server and as
long as your your content so it can
balance between the two of them and say
and if it's working on feedback
algorithm to know which is the more busy
server and so on then you can use this
as a as a mechanism for lumpy
scalability of your system and it
automatically means that if one of the
machines machines go down the overall
amount of power you have is reduced so
as in the redundant element case we have
a slower machine as backup and systems
get slower if the primary machine fails
it's kind of the same thing in the load
balance case because if you have less
total power the applications gonna get
slower but you can use your resources
more efficiently in the case where
nothing fails so that's probably the
that the core cost benefit yes
definitely the case of not having a
machine or machine sat around doing
nothing and in some cases you sometimes
it's difficult to avoid that things like
firewalls for example you don't
necessarily want to firewalls in
operation at one time so you may decide
that what you really want is a warm
standby that is the redundant element
that it's just waiting there to come on
board should the first one fail for most
other things like switches and routers
and servers you really want to get some
use out of what you paid for but that
the the this thing the what we what we
found interesting is we as we were going
through this was there's this this thing
of where is the tipping point between
active redundant and load balanced
there's almost again if you go from the
technology direction there's almost an
assumption that say if you have a set of
Windows 2000 servers you will cluster
them together well why you know is that
the best configuration for your
particular organization the particular
application you're creating it may be
better to have a far smaller capacity
server and that can give a minimal
amount of functionality for people that
they can get by with while the main
servers brought back on stream if that's
acceptable to your application why get
into the complexity of introducing
something that's got to manage server on
analyze the load on the servers and and
distribute load between them so now I'm
a client in one of your applications I
use your application the primary server
stops crashes so I'm kind of magically
redirected to the backup machine or in
case of load balancer elements just to a
different one of those machines what
happens to my my current process to my
data to my session is it replicated or
any ideas there it's funny you should
ask that yes there are there are whole
things to consider this is I mean hit
the nail on the head here that that as
soon as you stop having one box that
housing your functionality a whole set
of other things spring up so great we've
got a really good motivation for having
multiple boxes whether that's one
failing over to the other or whether
that's load balancing between but we
immediately get into the issue of as you
say what what about my session data
because we're in the land of Internet
applications we're inherently stateless
in terms of there's no ongoing
connection between the client and the
services so there's no way of
maintaining that now the waters muddied
slightly because obviously in HTTP 1.1
and certain application servers you can
have sticky sessions so potentially you
could create that ongoing connection but
the question is do you really want to
and you get into this the question of to
solve the problem one of the solutions
to the problem is to make the clients
sticky to a particular server then great
your
State is always there the problem being
if that's the server that falls over or
if that's the server that's really
heavily loaded you either have no
performance or poor performance so in
order to deliver high level of
performance and scalability particularly
you need to be able to move clients
between different servers and in doing
so you need to move their their current
session state so you get into this this
thing of great as in a simple system we
can maintain our session in memory that
won't work because we can't transfer it
across easily so there's got to be
something that's shared between the
systems that they can all see in order
to hold this state so that brings us
onto that the concerns are having to
have a common store and that store for
persistent information so common
persistent store so sharing between the
application servers a repository for
that sort of state and again this then
brings up questions where does it live
it could be one of the application
servers okay that's a fairly simple you
know fairly straightforward thing to do
but and two things one it isn't fit with
the style of an application server and
if that application server happens to be
the one that crashes everybody loses
their states so we're getting it into
this thing of okay or we've got to have
something this not not one of the things
we're expecting to fail so not one the
application servers so fine we can
create ourselves a database server so we
know we designed to put it in a database
or potentially just honest you know some
sort of RPC accessible States TOI
doesn't particularly matter but we have
some form of state store and fine okay
so that lives on a separate box great
okay so that's so if any of our
application service falls over they can
all use and all go back to the same
source of states ah okay a couple of
issues now then one is that we've now
have another single point of failure
which is our storage ask our state
storage box so we then have to apply the
same principles there we say okay well
what hat what do we want to do we can
have an active redundant state storage
or we can have load balance state
storage and we just backup before going
heading heading Haring down that line
what happens to the state you know we've
got so when a client request comes in
we're obviously dealing with that in
memory we've got variables and memory
block that we know
customer we're dealing with we've picked
a cookie up off their off their
connection so we've managed to identify
that that's customer but given that our
state is on that separate separates
database or state server now what do we
how do we get it I get hold of it so we
got to make data but start again make
database calls or our pcs across to the
state server to retrieve the state and
we've also got to make sure we make
equivalent calls at the end of this at
the end of the call to med to push it
back out again the problems we get into
there again another another nest of
problems appears below that because we
get into the question of performance
with degrading performance because we're
adding extra cross machine calls and
also we've got different and more
complex and more interesting error
handling scenarios of what happens if
the states if this if the system crashes
partway through before it managed to
write the state back one thing I did in
in a system I once built or was involved
in building was that we'd keep the
session in memory of the sticky session
machine and we'd ride it out to database
but not whenever something changed but
at well-defined synchronization points
that would mean that if the current
machine crashes you would continue your
session not exactly at the point where
you left but at a well-defined safe
point so that was a compromise between
having users not lose any data and the
performance penalty you'd have to pay if
you write back everything to the
database indeed in that sense there's a
there's a good sort of trade-off there
between the amount of performance you
bleed through writing everything back
and the amount of benefit you get you
can't say that you should always do X
and this is one of the key things here
is that if you have a technology out of
the box it's tempting to say that you
look at the pro prescriptive guidance
from the vendor and they say this is how
you build this sort of application and
say well ok maybe this is how you build
you this sort of application if you are
eBay or if you are Amazon because they
tend to show a top end sort of
application with all the bells and
whistles and all the failover and all
the load balancing and everything else
the problem is is if your application is
somewhere between very straightforward
one
and Amazon you need some of the things
but not all of the things and the
trade-offs you then you need to figure
out what trade-offs you can make
yourself and that's as you say that sort
of thing where is it good enough to have
a session from about five minutes ago if
your state doesn't change that often
yeah great for that for the one person
it inconveniences the thousand who never
notice will will carry on working quite
merrily I mean obviously we're talking
about common persistent stores we're
getting to two other things if we if
we're saying that our common data store
has to be duplicated in some way either
active redundant or load balanced we get
into the question if we've got two
instances of it how do we know which
ones got the right data so we get into
the fact that we have to have data
replication between the two instances of
the data store so we don't go deeply
into styles of replication and issues
around replication per se but the the
the data replication pattern we have in
there fits in with the active redundant
elements to say if you have data there
then you have to have data replication
in order to make this work because
otherwise you'll failover to something
that's so far out of dates and this it's
your users on aren't going to accept it
is it fair to assume that your database
will take care of that because I often
you know see those pictures where it
says database and Oracle will take care
of the replication so is that are they
mature enough so is that is that a valid
point from the systems I'd worked on I
would say yes but again it's easy
your mileage may vary and I have fairly
straightforward no I've had fairly
straightforward requirements for state
management in the business systems that
I've worked on so the amount of
replication you get out of the box from
something like sequel server or Oracle
does there's done the job quite
adequately obviously if you get more
complex requirements you've got
different data centers and so on then
everything becomes far more complex and
the solutions I've seen where you have
to say that multiple data centers the
sort of solutions have seen people put
in place so I'm all to do with having
things like storage networks so they
actually address it at the file level
rather than at the
trying to get the software instances of
databases to synchronize with each other
which seems to be a simpler solution in
the replication you talk about is
primarily asynchronous so it's not like
you have a two-phase commit to two
database instances which I think Oracle
can do also but rather what you're
talking about is this asynchronous thing
where the slave database is always ten
seconds behind or something or did I get
this wrong the requirements I've had
have been generally been addressed by
having as you say the master slave
pairing which which parallels well with
the active redundant so your your active
server is is running you know you you
get a fairly powerful active server
that's running all the time and then if
it does fail it fails over to a lower
power machine that has been clustered
together it's been synchronized so it's
been getting all that all the all the
updates shipped to it from the master as
it's gone so it can start back up from a
fairly fairly accurate location but
again one of the things we get into here
is in both cases it's worse if you're
trying to do multi master
synchronization but in either case you
get a lot of you're going to have to
have a lot of traffic between the two
system so you're if you're putting a lot
of data into your system all of that
data's got to go across the boundary
between the two database servers so it
implies more cost more performance
degradation and so on or a balance
between somewhere between the two so you
can spend loads of money so that you
don't notice the performance degradation
or you know you accept that the
performance is gonna is going to drop a
little but there are other things then
we need to get into so if we have if
we're failing over onto a lower capacity
server so we can be doing this at
different levels so there's the database
can failover there's the application
server can failover but also the we only
defied the need to do in most systems to
separate out the web in the application
server now the the the reasons for this
there we went it was an interesting
discussion on this because a lot of
systems it was a typical pattern mining
thing a lot of systems we saw did this
but you get into the question of okay
why yes
what is the reason for separating the
apple of the application server in the
web
so typically you'll see the web server
sitting in the demilitarized zone
the application server sitting inside
the the inner firewall and so you get
this this this two hop thing though if
somebody's coming in to request some
dynamic functionality they hit the web
server the reverse proxy in the web
server go drills back through the
firewall to the application server the
application server runs the software
generates the result and then it goes
back through the two hops back to the
client so because you're doing an extra
hop going through a firewall as well
you've got orders of magnitude more
overhead than you would have if you put
everything on the web server
so having drilled down through this the
two main reasons we came up with here
for why people do this primarily
security so you're moving the
programmatic bit the bit with the JSP
Zoar the ASP s back one level behind the
internal firewall and you can apply
different and levels of patching you can
divide the different security measures
to that machine than to the web server
so eat whether that's whether that's the
case that you you harden the web server
you make the web server absolutely
bulletproof but the application server
is less secure because it's inside
you're behind your firewall or
alternatively you may take particular
actions on the application server to
guard against programmatic attacks but
for overflows and so on that you
wouldn't you know you wouldn't
necessarily apply to the web server so
there's a security question of pushing
the the dynamic functionality further
back into a safer zone and there's also
but the actual profile the performance
profile because we got this thing where
you might have systems might look
kite-shaped for example so if you
imagine a kind of traditional kite
diamond-shaped kite it's the top of the
kite with your front ends at end of your
system you have say like two web servers
there and two if all they're serving is
static content so where HTML pages CSS
images and so on then even if you've got
quite a lot of traffic quite a lot of
users they can probably handle it quite
well just two of them whereas when you
get into application servers they're
running up huge amount you know huge
amounts of processing to turn things
around you may want 5 6 10 15 of them to
service your user base
so you get it you get a certain it's
it's it's so it's it goes from the top
of the kite and it expands out to where
the the main crossbar is and then it
goes back again you know it goes back to
a tail again because again at your
database level you have two database
servers and so this this is that this is
where we got into this seems like the
the width of the kite will vary
depending on the type of system but also
you know you make other systems where
you have a an inverse triangle with the
point of the triangle be in the database
servers then you have a few application
servers in the middle and lots of web
servers because you've got lots of
static content potentially so it depends
on the type of system as to what shape
it will look like so what you're saying
is that the question of how you
distribute your layers on two tiers
should be determined by your basically
load requirements so if you have them on
different tiers you can load balanced or
or or you can give different amounts of
power to each of the logical layers
because there are different physical
tiers well this gets into an interesting
in the interesting point here because
the the actual location of the logical
layers if you take the typical
presentation application business beta I
had this this this real the real road to
Damascus thing about how everything
fitted together as we're going through
some of this because of coming from I
suppose it's just because the systems
I'd worked on up to that point the use
of the web server had been they actually
had systems where the ASP Stroke jsps
had been affected on the web server so
it had the web server then calling
across back to the application server
which is serving things like ejbs and so
on and when you step back and look at
this you think well this is absolute
insanity because you're making lots of
RPC calls between two physical machines
whereas really what you know what what
you need to need to do is again it's see
the inside the box you partition
logically and the inside of your box is
your application server the only thing
the web server should really be doing
is feeding static content and delegating
everything else back off to the
application server and so there's a
section that discusses it why why tears
and lots of catastrophe which is based
on a conversation I had with someone on
a training course who used to say if
something was bad he's a catastrophe and
there's I was discussing this through
with him when I had there this this this
road to Damascus sudden realization and
it it is I I find this quite
enlightening in some ways because if you
read a lot of the vendor stuff they are
very loose on their use of terminology
tears and layers and and elements and
servers and so on and they all
intermingles and it can give you a very
skewed view of the world and how that
you know how they think the world should
be and I get the feeling sometimes that
somebody say somebody within son years
and years ago probably said hey you know
if you have the ejbs on a separate tier
of machines then the JSP and servlets
can talk to them and also the thick
clients can talk to them as well it's
like oh yes that's a great idea in the
case that you have both thick and thin
clients but for most of us we don't have
them we have one or the other so yeah if
you have thick clients you've got to
have a separate tier of video be servers
if you got thin clients there's
absolutely no need to have a separate
area be service and probably there's no
absolutely no need to have EGA B's but
that's a different story
we've had this discussion on the podcast
I guess a couple of times so are there
any to optimize the performance of an
application server a lot of things are
obviously done by the applications of a
vendor is there anything that's
particularly particularly worth
mentioning with regards to things like
caching or limiting the amount of users
that you can use in case you're in it
backup or something well one of the you
say you expect out of the box with any
modern application server environment
you expect things like resource pooling
you need to have that in order to
achieve the scalability you need to be
able to acquire late release early the
other thing you know the other thing
that's useful is
caching mechanisms to those obviously
data that doesn't change much over time
so fine you wanna you wanna cash cashed
in your servers rather than having to go
back and fetch you from the database
every time one of the things we're
getting to though with with if we got
active redundant failover or even if
even in the case of load balancing if
our if our amount of processing power
drops below a certain level then we can
we run the risk then that everybody
visiting all right ecommerce sites start
to perceive very slow performance so
again we get it with a trade-off
scenario here what we can do is we can
limit the number of connections at the
front end so like at the webserver end
or the front of the application server
which means that in some of the cases
then some customers coming to the site
will not be able to get a connection so
it's obviously bad for them
but what it does mean is for the
remaining people who are still on the
site they're getting a more consistent
level performance so if we know that the
back end as the reduces level
performance we can wind down the number
of connections we can admit in so the
people still the people who get in could
still get a responsive site and then
other people get told politely I'm sorry
we can't we can't help you at the moment
so that's this sort of sort of things we
need to think about at the front end but
there's also considerations at the back
end because one of the things marketing
people and so on love to do is play with
figures you know if they want to know
how many people have visited the site
what sort of patterns of usage they've
made of the site and so on all of that
is stored away in your database is your
live databases if people buy and if
people are performing large queries on
those databases doing data mining
crunching trying to figure out what the
optimal paths are what products they
should associate with which other
products are so on there's two
completely different user sets they're
two different sets of functional
requirements on the system one for a
quick turnaround for a customer coming
from the web and the other for a high
program and processing so what are in
that case what you can do is take it's
what we call offline reporting basically
take a snapshot of your data put it on a
separate database and let the marketing
people play with it to their heart's
content is the because generally what
they're doing doesn't have to have the
latest and greatest data its historical
trend
they're looking at and also often those
databases have the same content but a
different structure or maybe the content
is pre aggregated to some level so you
can run data warehousing functions that
functionality more easily I guess so
that's not a reason to have a separate
database correct yes it you want to if
you want to create particular views on
the data or particular combined tables
and so on you shouldn't have to put that
overhead on your live production server
okay so I think this completes the
parents that deal with system
performance performance as I learned
from the discussion are also performance
in the sense of availability so it's
basically called run time patterns so
anyway so the next the next kind of
patterns we want to talk about are the
system control patterns they probably
have to do with the idea of keeping the
system up and running and monitoring
these kinds of things yes this is one of
my personal soap boxes the the the
things about scalability availability
performance tend to be what I call
front-end stakeholder concerns so in any
system you have the the initially the
users of the system you have the
sponsors who are paying for it you have
the version one development team all of
whom have an interest in the first
version of the system and they are the
front-end stakeholders and generally
their requirements are listened to and
generally met what you then have is a
set of what I call back in stakeholders
so the operations and team the support
team and the version two onwards
development team who've got to live with
all the stuff that was put together in
the first place and this is where you
get into the and also not only that but
they've they've got a live system to
deal with so they're responsible for
keeping that system going so if if
things go pear-shaped it's not going to
be any of the front-end stakeholders to
get hold out of bed at 2:00 a.m. in the
morning to come and fix the system it's
gonna be one of the backend stakeholders
so they have a set of very very little
judgment concerns about what
requirements are in the system and what
the main the core thing is that they
need to know what's going on in the
system to be able to diagnose it which
is where we get into initially continual
is reporting so the idea that every
component in the system should be
capable of reporting its status of
what's going on in the inside it the
amount of information will depend on the
component with the type of component and
it'll also depend on the audience for
the information but basically that's
that's the core basis of continually
continual state of reporting on top of
that then and obviously the fine things
are generating information but what does
it mean so what we what we need to draw
out of that is is it operating correctly
there are there are different levels of
this has it stopped working completely
or is it nearing its its capacity in
which case we start to need to take take
take measures about it so that's where
we get into the the operational
monitoring side of things and using that
that continually reported information to
provide us the basis for that monitoring
and alerting should things fall over or
go beyond thresholds so there's that's
operational monitoring and alerting is
more event-driven so there so that's an
event-driven part of the system that you
assume the systems going okay unless it
pops up and tells you that it isn't you
then get the other side of the coin well
you actually want to know how the system
is doing this could be in several from
several aspects one is from the
operations point of view you want to see
when things are warming up you want to
see so you want to see that the the
profiles that the trends of what's
what's happening across your servers and
the only thing is you don't have time to
wade through all the logs so what you
need is some representation of what's
going on so this is where we get into
the early arriving system overview
because really what you all you need is
is an at-a-glance view of how your
system is running with with indicators
of like red and the green indicators so
everything's green you know all the
application servers are green oh the web
servers are amber I wonder why that is
Tara let's go and have a look at the log
so it gives you know you start from the
top level where to drill down into what
needs looking at at the moment which you
would never get if you have to wade
through the logs yourself
how would you say how much if you build
an application like that how much of
this monitoring logging alerting stuff
is something you have to do yourself how
much do you get for free per application
servers or SNMP tools or HP openview or
whatever so how how much out of the box
functionality can you get there I think
it's there is a reasonable amount amount
of the Box functionality but if you get
say like hardware pieces of hardware
like Reuters they're generally very well
served for SNMP and sells so you can you
can know you've got a fairly well
defined object model whether it's s CI m
and things like that where you can hook
it up to things that are already built
to take that information and you you
know you can just configure it on the
device itself and away you go
it gets more tricky when you get to the
application level because you then then
you're into the area the way you're
reliant on individual coders in many
cases to put in to do the right thing in
the code and this is where it's
interesting one of the papers here that
Europe lop is about logging not so much
the mechanisms of logging because that's
been covered very well previously but
more what you lock and when you log it
so the information you log and it's that
sort of thing and we touched on it
briefly with it with a pattern called
three category logging but the guys who
are presenting the paper here that take
it they're taking those sort of ideas on
far further so figuring out what you
should log based on who it's what the
audience is because there are many
different audiences in your application
okay so no now you you notice that that
something's wrong you see an alert that
you have too many users which is good by
the way maybe too many customers but so
what do you do do you need capabilities
of dynamically changing some aspects of
the configuration or what do you do
about it
this is a good question because it's in
the security world they talk about the
detection of an intrusion and the fact
that great okay we can put up all these
things to detect something that goes
wrong but if we can't do anything about
it there's what's the point of detecting
in the first place so what we need to be
able to do is notice to configure the
system based on what's going on too
the values of things as I mentioned
earlier on if you want to throttle down
the number of users if something's
forward if one of your servers has
fallen over the back end then you need
to be able to do that at runtime you
can't reboot all the servers you know go
in and change your configuration file
and reboot the server no that doesn't
work if you if you've got a highly
available system so you need to identify
key values key parameters to your system
and make them dynamically adjustable so
you can go in and say change a value in
a database that's read on a regular
basis or have a refresh mechanism like
was which one it was now it's a long
time since I use UNIX there was a
particular kill signal on UNIX to get
things to refresh themselves to reread
the configuration parameters that sort
of mechanism in order to be able to
change the running in the running system
or in Java maybe use a gem X dynamic
configuration for this kind of stuff yes
yes and it so there are there are many
ways of skinning accounts in this case
and it the the complexity and
sophistication will depend very much on
whether you you know how much of this
you need it may be good enough just to
have a couple of values in a database
and relied the fact on the fact that the
next time the components instantiated it
picks up the new values so in just since
we already mentioned Europe lob and this
interview is actually recorded that the
Europe lob 2006 conference and closed
it'll say in biome Germany and there is
another paper by Paris of Keller you
about dynamic reconfiguration in service
based systems or something like that so
he talks a bit about this idea of
monitoring evaluating the problems and
then adapting the quality of service
just as a side note will put it into the
show notes so the next one is probably
related to security I guess because we
didn't talk about that too much yet and
I think it's an important concern in
enterprise systems we lumped together
the sort of maintainability the
operations issues together with security
because security spans you've got to
think of it upfront but it's also
something that's an ongoing it part of
the system that you may change the
security model the security levels
certainly over time and so we started
I'm the most obvious
and the people use in terms of Internet
security the Demilitarized Zone so the
idea of an external firewall stroke
Rooter an internal firewall strat Rooter
and something between that will serve
the outside world and is potentially is
like a sacrificial area it's things you
put in there you know have got to be
either expendable or more highly armored
than your your internal servers
something so that was that was that the
primary like defensive security for the
systems were that we'd worked on would
be getting to other other other issues
with if people are trying to break into
your systems one of the things that can
give them a a real boost is if they can
get an idea of the topology of what they
what they're trying to to break into so
if you have well named servers for
example you know directory server web
server one web server two web server
three database server one database
server two and so on
then great it's great from the
maintainability point of view it
features the figures very highly but
from the security point of view it's
less good because it gives people an
easy ability to map all they need is is
the names of your servers and they can
map out what functionality is on each
one and start to try and guess how to
break it so there's that's part the one
of the things we address with a pattern
called information obscurity of saying
well potentially these by changing the
names of these servers then it will be
less accessible they make yours you know
your system more more secure through
obscurity and these the the same sort of
thing applies to you know you can take
that all the way down to encryption of
credit card details and so on of having
some those are probably the end the two
ends of the scale but some way of
obscuring the data that you're working
with it all adds an overhead so
obviously in credit card encryption
it will we've got a decrypt in order to
use it so it's a processing overhead and
as I said in the case of obscuring names
of things it's a maintainability
overhead and so that was that the the
other thing in terms of static security
that we noticed Pete
have been used on systems the other two
things were to do with data in transit
so the the key thing like essentially
SSL and its relations we said okay what
are you doing here again looking round
they weren't then that time there
weren't many security pattern so this
before Marcus Schumacher and company
started put together the security
patterns book and so we looked at again
we looked around and we couldn't find
this is a general thing we were quite
surprised that nobody had put together
patterns in this area before so in the
same with the security we looked around
we thought well nobody's actually put
together a pattern about SSL to describe
essentially the core principle behind
SSL they describe why we do it what the
forces are in terms of creating you know
wanting to create a secure connection
but there's an overhead associated with
creating the connection and so on so we
we put a pattern called secure channels
to discuss that and also known partners
to discuss the the more secure VPN type
networks where you've got a business
partner connecting in and making you
making use of your systems again across
public internet and therefore needing to
get involved in authentication with
using certificates okay so I think
looking at the in our concept for the
show this completes the system control
patterns I think so we have built a
system that runs nicely that's reliable
that's fast at scales we have a means of
keeping it running monitoring alerting
people changing stuff dynamically if
things should go wrong so what's missing
I guess is a way of evolving the system
over time once requirements change so
there are probably a couple of
architectural building blocks that you
can use to make a system potentially
adaptable over changing requirements or
just over time yes I mean one of the one
of the hardest things I've found over
the past few years is getting out of
business people a correct estimation of
the number of customers they expect for
internet facing websites they will
either be wildly over optimistic
at the top or they'll be understated and
so that whichever sin you know if you
tend as an engineer you tend to ends of
may try and cut through this and figure
out what the real figures are gonna be
but you realize that potentially there
could be a very successful marketing
campaign that suddenly your load starts
to rise over a very short period of time
so you need to be able to adapt your
system in a very quick way but also you
need to be able to extend and expand
your system over the course of years and
in a predictable way so one of the
things you get into in terms of the
short term evolution of the system is
we've talked about having scalability
through having say three application
servers and a content switching front of
them channeling the load to whichever
the least lightly loaded obviously at
some point in time if we're successful
and we will start hitting 60 70 80 %
usage on all three servers and we want
to add a fourth server and equally if
one of the servers goes down we want to
shove another one in there fairly
quickly
now what the issue there is that the
system that's doing the load balancing
needs to be able to identify that there
is a new server there and to start using
it so you get into this this I know that
you need to have dynamic discovery of
the system elements so a new element
pops up we know we stick a new machine
in the rack we plug it into the network
we power it up and we want the contents
which to say aha new system right here
you go here are some customers in some
users for you and an off you go so that
applies at a variety of levels from
hardware to just down to the components
you know if you've got a new type of
components if you have a consistent
interface to your components and you you
know you plug a new type in then you
want to the system to recognize it and
start using it and making it available
rather than again having to shut the
system down in order bring it back up
again so there's that that's one at one
approach to evolving the system another
another thing is obviously if we've got
three service we go back to our three
servers heating 80% load another thing
we can do is you can stick more hardware
in them one of the the tails that that
that Paul told them when we're
discussing some of the discuss in the
book and we were working
our experiences was about who is trying
to figure out how best to make an
application more memory efficient
because they were running out of memory
the early prototypes they knew they were
running out of memory so they did a few
initial investigations and they realized
the easiest thing was just to buy an on
memory stick more memory because they
have memory slots so this we get into
the idea of expandable hardware so
rather than when you're buying your
initial hardware rather than buying a
fully kitted out fully fully slot and
plotted up machine and then having as
soon as you hit the performance bandit
on it you've got to throw it away by one
that's got additional slots so it may be
a little bit more cost to start with but
the incremental cost of having to throw
the first machine away and build another
one you've got to buy the big machine
anyway and you know you've got the
problems of any any sense of rebuilding
exercise is always dangerous because you
know you've got to be sure you're doing
exactly the same thing you did last time
so that's that's it this sort of thing
there one of the things that that really
helps in terms of evolution has been
this is what we turn the virtual
platform so this isn't unfortunate when
when you when that first comes up people
tend to think of things like VMs yes
now what we're thinking up here is more
like a set of API is if you like for a
platform so one of those api's could be
j2ee equally one of those open eyes
could be dotnet although we probably get
less efficient and less less benefits
from net than j2ee in the fact that
putatively you could replace your j2ee
insulator with a different one what so
takes them to get away from the actual
virtual machine and framework side think
about something like a mail server so on
Windows as there's the map lis API so if
we needed to do the mail outs I
mentioned earlier on that potential your
system able to mail out to all the
ecommerce customers if you want to do
that we need to talk to a mail server to
do it for us now if we say ok our
software that does this talk to the
mapping interface then potentially this
the actual particular mail server behind
that we can just replace with a
different one should we find that there
are problems with it's either
performance problems or functionality
problems so it's creating this this
virtual
said the set of api's that insulate your
application from the underlying
particular platforms operating systems
and so on which could be called a
technology independent architecture just
to to reference indeed to reference a
reference revenue player yes okay so one
thing we didn't talk about yet but
something that I've seen in many
projects is that people talk about
staging environments and testing
environments so we have several
installations of your system
one for playing around one for verifying
that its production ready and then the
production system itself any specific
thoughts on this one one of the problems
you get with that with migration is that
you've got to be absolutely sure if you
can migrate from one environment to
another that the the test environment
for example you've been working in is a
fair representation of the live
environment you can be deploying into
and so obviously did you say people
employ a staging environment that is a
pretty much live it's an exact duplicate
of the live environment so the question
you get into is how do you make an exact
duplicate of the live environment and
one of the approaches here is to
actually host your staging environment
on the live production servers but
partitions so for example if you're on a
I actually have a different UNIX
instance so finally if the if the
staging environment went pear-shaped as
you were warming it up then it's not
going to affect your your production
server the service now so that the again
this is one of the monitors it's a
particular approach you may not be able
to take this approach depending on what
sort of hardware and software you're
running on but it's if you can do this
sort of thing then potentially what you
can do is is you you create your staging
environment there you deploy your new
version of your software you go through
your sanity checks and make sure
everything's working okay
and then we can do is you can migrate
your your your user base across onto
that's new software on what what was is
beautifully the staging environment so
in effect what it says is after you have
verified that something works as
advertised you don't want to do another
micro you don't want to change things
again but rather just move your make
make this test and
former test environment or staging
environment to be the production
environment from there on because we
verified that this one works yes now
that's not the great benefit of it
because you've got to that you'd as you
say you don't have to change things
again because every time you change
thing there's obviously risk of getting
it wrong and so then once you use of all
migrated over we tend to do is you tend
to clean up what was the production
environment and that then becomes the
staging environment so this is the
swappable bit so basically you're
swapping backwards and forwards between
the typically to application server
instances running on the same piece of
hardware and you obviously get a start
running stuff on that staging
environment its impact its taking up
some resources that could be used for
production but the whole idea with the
staging environment should be just a
sanity check that you've got things
right all your performance testing and
everything else to be further back down
that's downstream before you before you
get to the the staging environment so
that's one one thing in terms of that
the the partitioning of the system and
then the final thing is about the data
and we're looking at evolution of
systems one of the things you get is is
if you need to upgrade your system
because your configuration data
structure has changed so you're adding
new features and new functionality maybe
your actual user data structures haven't
changed your schemas haven't changed but
the the data that the data use
internally to the application is
configuration information has if
everything if all your data is held
together intermingled then basically
you've got to upgrade you've got to hit
the whole database and upgrade the whole
database and even if you're not hitting
those particular tables there's always a
chance you'll screw something up and
then you've got to have rollback for
that user data and the problem with it
with the user data or with the what we
what we turn we turn the internal stuff
the configuration of the system managed
data so it's data that the system itself
originates and potentially you can
recreate the problem with the rest of
the data is potentially you can't
recreate it which is why we need to get
into backups and so on but even then we
don't we don't want to damage it if we
if we can help her so if we separate out
this the the user the externally sourced
data from the system managed data it
means that potentially we can upgrade
the system manage data database
completely independently of the
externally sourced data
which means we're reducing the risk
profile here quite a lot and one of the
major issues I have with with the system
and working at the moment is the fact
that it's it's a hosted system and it
bundles the user data together with the
system manage data and this is causing
us all sorts of problems because we
can't migrate the two separately okay so
I guess this summarizes roughly 50
minutes of enterprise architecture so of
course it's quite unrealistic to have
the wisdom of enterprise architects put
into 50 minutes it's even probably a bit
more realistic to put all this wisdom
into a book and the one from which we
basically scrapped this this podcast so
so as a kind of last word to the
listeners do you want to say a couple of
additional words which benefits people
would get if they would read the book
because they the book has a couple of
additional sections we kind of didn't
cover in in this podcast well I think
one of the one of the the things we
tried to do with the book was to walk
through how you would actually apply the
pattern so Giants trying to take three
or four different scenarios and actually
look given those scenarios which of the
patterns you would apply because one of
the things we don't we're not we're not
saying is that here's a book for the
patterns going away and apply all of
these in the next system you build
because some of them will apply to some
systems and not to others so we hope
that by doing the walk throughs you'll
be able to see able to identify a system
that's similar to the one you're working
on and to get an idea of which of the
patterns are probably most suited to
your particular situation okay so as you
you might have got the point who should
buy the book
so Andy thank you for being on the show
and yeah thank you Marcus thank you
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at se - radio dotnet
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Holley for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details